A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Government and Law Program, Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe FA627
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Government and Law Program, Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe
1970-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jaffe, Sanford M.
Ford Foundation
FA627
1.32 Cubic Feet
The Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe, Program Officer and Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's National Affairs Division from 1968 to 1981, document his activities in the Government & Law program between 1970 and 1981. The files were transferred to the Foundation Archives in April 1982. The office files consist of 1.25 linear feet of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and minutes. They are divided into two series: Select Correspondence and Chronological Files. Arrangement within the series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Jaffe's office.
Biographical / Historical
Sanford M. Jaffe was a member of the Ford Foundation staff from March 1968 until November 1981. During this period, he held the following positions:
• 1979 Program Officer Government and Law National Affairs • 1973 POIC Government and Law National Affairs • 1969 Program Officer Government and Law National Affairs • 1968 Program Officer Social Development National Affairs • 1968 Program Advisor Social Development National Affairs
Sanford Jaffe was born February 12, 1932. He received his Bachelor of Arts (RA.) degree in 1954 from Rutgers University, and was elected Phi Beta Kappa. In 1957, Jaffe earned the Bachelor of Laws (LL.R) degree from the Harvard Law School.
Prior to Jaffe's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1958-1959, New Jersey Supreme Court - Law Secretary to Chief Justice • 1959-1961, Essex County Prosecutor's Office - Assistant Prosecutor • 1961-1966, U.S. Attorney's Office - Chief, Criminal Division • 1966-1967, Assistant Attorney General, Washington, D.C. - Special Assistant • 1967-1968, Governor's Select Committee on Civil Disorder, New Jersey - Executive Director
After his departure from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Jaffe served as Visiting Fellow, Institute of Judicial Administration of New York City.
Scope and Contents
The National Affairs/Government and Law Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe consist of chronological files, correspondence, inter-office memoranda and minutes. They document the activities of Mr. Jaffe between 1970 and 1981 in his position as Program Officer and Program Officer in Charge.
The Office Files demonstrate two key interests of Mr. Jaffe: development of the fields of public interest law and conflict resolution.
Arrangement
The National Affairs/Government and Law Office Files of Sanford M. Jaffe are divided into two series:
I. Select Correspondence
II. Chronological Files
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Select Correspondence, I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Select Correspondence, is arranged by subject. The subjects are in chronological order from the date of the initial document. Within each folder the documents are in reverse chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Select Correspondence, contains .25 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda and minutes of the Public Interest Law Advisory Committee (PILAC). This series documents PILAC activities (1970-77) both in recommending action on grant proposals and in developing a theoretical framework for "public interest" law and practice (see also log file L71-328). This series also documents some of Mr. Jaffe's work in the area of conflict resolution. Series I includes memoranda and correspondence on the establishment of the National Institute for Dispute Resolution (see also grant file PA 83-205), the Gay Head [MA] Taxpayers Association Wampanoag Tribal Council dispute and Jaffe's incoming correspondence on his New Approaches to Conflict Resolution: A Ford Foundation Report (1978).
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series 1 is not available for research. It was not transferred to RAC and is therefore not an active part of the collection.
  - Public Interest Law Advisory Committee Correspondence, 1970 - 1977
  - Public Interest Law Advisory Committee Minutes, 1971 - 1977
  - Conflict Resolution, Paper-Comments, 1977 - 1978
  - Gay Head (MA) Taxpayers Association-Mampanoag Tribal Council Dispute, 1977
  - National Institute for Dispute Resolution, 1980 - 1981
- Chronological Files, II
  Series II, Chronological Files, are in reverse chronological order. Within each folder the documents are also in reverse chronological order.
  Series II, Chronological Files, consists of one linear foot of Mr. Jaffe's outgoing correspondence and memoranda including routine transmittal notes to colleagues, reminders to grantees of their annual narrative and financial reports, and acknowledgements of invitations to annual meetings and conferences. In addition to the administrative matters, this series documents Mr. Jaffe's work in developing the field of public interest law. Letters to PILAC members and to Joel Handler, Burton Weisbrod and Mauro Cappelletti are note worthy in this respect.
  The chronological files include correspondence to: Public Interest Law Advisory Committee (PILAC) members Whitney North Seymour, Sr., Bernard G. Segal, Orison S. Marden, and William T. Gossett, to individuals at the Center for Law in Public Interest, the American Arbitration Association, the Native Americans Rights Fund, Vera Institute of Justice, the American Civil Liberties Union Foundation, the Citizens Communication Center, the Natural Resources Defense Council, Center for Law and Social Policy, the Environmental Defense Fund and the Education Law Center, and to colleagues at the Ford Foundation.
  - Chronological Files, 1978 October (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 December - October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 September - July (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 June - April (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 March - January (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 1975 December - October (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 1975 September - July (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 1975 June - April (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 1975 March – January (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 December - October (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 September - July (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 June - May (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 April - March (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Chronological Files, 1974 February - January (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chronological Files, 1973 December - October (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chronological Files, 1973 September – August (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Chronological Files, 1973 July - June (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Chronological Files, 1973 May - April (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Chronological Files, 1973 March - January (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 December - November (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 October - September (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 August - July (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 June - May (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 April - March (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chronological Files, 1972 February - January (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 December (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 November (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 October (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 September (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 August (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 July (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 June (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 April (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 March (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Chronological Files, 1971 January (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 February (Box 3, Folder 50)